Mss.497.3.H39
American Philosophical Society
Correspondence on Indian names, 1854-1860
Mss.497.3.H39
American Philosophical Society
1.0 Volume(s) 1 volume, 22 items
This volume of letters Sebastian Ferris Streeter and John Henry Alexander, both of the Maryland Historical Society, relating to efforts of Henry to secure information on Indian names and to obtain travel grants from the Maryland Historical Society, the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, and the Smithsonian Institution. There are letters from Edward Ballard of Maine Historical Society, and P. W. Leland and Usher Parsons of Rhode Island Historical Society, concerning New England Indian place names. There is also a letter (1854) to J. Francis Fisher and others of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania, in response to a circular appeal, on Indian names of Northampton County, Pennsylvania (929.4 H39).
1 volume; 22 items.
Henry, Mathew Schropp, 1790-1862
Volume 1
Box-folder 1
Related Archival Materials note
Letter to J. Francis Fisher and members of the Historical Society of Pennsylvania regarding Indian names of Northampton County, Pennsylvania (929.4 H39):
Gives county lists based on old deeds. Accompanied by a map of 1752, traced from Melish's Map of Pennsylvania (1826), but showing Indian place names. Principal source for place names is Heckewelder, with additional note by Henry. Offers to do more, if the Historical Society is interested.
General note
Freeman Guide 85, plus individual letters.
Arrangement note
The letters are listed in the order they are arranged in the volume.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Received and accessioned, 04/1914 (51119).
Alexander, J. H. (John Henry), 1812-1867.; Ballard, Edward, 1820-1897; Fisher, Joshua Francis, 1807-1873; Historical Society of Pennsylvania.; Leland, P. W.; Maine Historical Society.; Maryland Historical Society.; Parsons, Usher, 1788-1868; Rhode Island Historical Society.; Smithsonian Institution.; Streeter, Sebastian Ferris; Indians of North America--Pennsylvania--Names; Names, Indian -- North America.
- Correspondence, 1857-1860
  - Letter to Matthew S. Henry, Jan. 17, 1857; 1; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Scope and Contents note
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 3p. Only J.H.Alexander can help with Indian names in Penna.and N.J. Asks for definition of Powhatan names.
  - Letter to Matthew S. Henry, Feb. 8, 1857; 2; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 6p. Cannot help with expenses to visit Indian tribes in Canada to study languages. Refers to Heckewelder. Concerning definitions of Powhatan names. Freeman Guide 3063.
  - Letter to [Matthew S. Henry], March 10-13, 1857; 3; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Baltimore; A.L.S. 8p. Concerning definitions of Indian names, expecially those of the Lenni Lenape and the Powhatans. Freeman Guide 1185.
  - Letter to Matthew S. Henry, March 27, 1857; 4; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 2p. Will ask Alexander if his letters should be forwarded to Henry. If the answer is no, that is final. Freeman Guide 1186.
  - Letter to Matthew S. Henry, March 30, 1857; 5; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 2p. Left correspondence with Alexander, and will forward it to Henry if he agrees. Concerning definition of Indian names, possibly Iroquoian. Freeman Guide 1186.
  - Letter to Matthew S. Henry, April 3, 1857; 6; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 3p. Enc. Forwarded letters to Henry, as Alexander's enclosed note recommends. Concerning study of Indian languages. For enclosure, see: ALexander to M.S. Henry; April 2, 1857 (497.3:H39, no.14). Freeman Guide 1186.
  - Letter to [Matthew S. Henry], May 2, 1857; 7; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 1p. Will write when he has time, for he has just returned from an extensive trip. Freeman Guide 1186.
  - Letter to [Matthew S. Henry], Sept. 22, 1857; 8; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 1p. Has been too busy to answer properly Can see Alexander. Freeman Guide 1186.
  - Letter to Matthew S. Henry, Oct. 14, 1857; 9; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 3p. No financial aid can be expected from Maryland, and Alexander says Henry is not encouraging. Freeman Guide 1186.
  - Letter to Matthew S. Henry, Jan. 14, 1858; 10; 7x4-1/2; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning publication of work on Indian names. Freeman Guide 3707.
  - Letter to Matthew S. Henry, Oct. 18, 1859; 11; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 2p.and end. Is too occupied to work on the hobby of Indian languages. No help from Maryland is possible on publications. Freeman Guide 1187.
  - Letter to [Matthew S. Henry], Nov. 10, 1859; 12; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 2p. Could not help in his request to locate certain documents.
  - Letter to Matthew S. Henry, undated; 13; 8x5; Streeter, Sebastian F. (Sebastian Ferris), 1810-1864
    A.L.S. 2p. Incomplete. Concerning the definitions of Indian names. Freeman Guide 1188.
  - Letter to M[atthew] S. Henry, Philadelphia, April 2, 1857; 14; 8x6-1/2; Alexander, J. H. (John Henry), 1812-1867
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 1p. Will confer with Henry at the Smithsonian about aid for Indian language studies. Enclosed originally in: Streeter to M.S.Henry; (497.3:H39,no.6). Freeman Guide 1110.
  - Letter to M[atthew] S. Henry, Philadelphia, April 17, 1857; 15; 8x5; Alexander, J. H. (John Henry), 1812-1867
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 4p. His knowledge of the sciences which Henry and the smithsonian aid. Refers to Schoolcraft in the study of Indian languages. Freeman Guide 1111.
  - Letter to M[atthew] S. Henry, Philadelphia, April 30, 1857; 16; 8x5; Alexander, J. H. (John Henry), 1812-1867
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 3p. Wishes the secretary of the Historical society of Pennsylvania to notify the Maryland historical society of plans to aid him study Delaware linguistics, then Henry and the Smithsonian might aid. Freeman Guide 1112.
  - Letter to M[atthew] S. Henry, Philadelphia, Aug. 21, 1857; 17; 8x5; Alexander, J. H. (John Henry), 1812-1867
    Baltimore, A.L.S. 2p. Chances that Henry and the Smithsonian will help on the study of Indian language. Freeman Guide 1113.
  - Maryland names, undated; 18; 8x5; Alexander, J. H. (John Henry), 1812-1867
    A.D. 4p. These names are based on Indian words. Freeman Guide 344.
  - Letter to Matthew S. Henry, Philadelphia, Dec. 31, 1859; 19; 8x5; Ballard, Edward, 1804-1870
    Brunswick, Me., A.L.S. 8p. Concerning Indian names in New England. Freeman Guide 346.
  - Letter to M[atthew] S. Henry, Philadelphia, Feb. 6-7, 1860; 20; 8x5; Ballard, Edward, 1804-1870
    Brunswick, Me., A.L.S. 12p. Concerning the Indians and their languages. Freeman Guide 346.
  - Letter to Matthew S. Henry, Jan. 22, 1860; 21; 8x5; Parsons, Usher, 1788-1868
    Providence, A.L.S. 3p. Concerning Indian place names in New England. Freeman Guide 359.
  - Letter to M[atthew] S. Henry, Jan. 9, 1860; 22; 9-3/4x8; Leland, P. Washington (Phineas Washington), 1798-1870
    Fall River, A.L.S. 2p. Sends copy of publication. Has worked on Algonquin dialects only. Refers to Parsons. Freeman Guide 357.